Guide to the Duke University Anniversaries Collection, 1937 - 2000 UA.01.06.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University Anniversaries collection
1937 - 2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
UA.01.06.0001
15 Linear Feet
Duke University has celebrated anniversaries of two major founding events: the establishment of continuous education at Brown's Schoolhouse in Randolph County, N.C., in 1838, and the creation of the Duke Endowment, which transformed Trinity College into Duke University in 1924. As a result, the institution commemorated the 100th Anniversary of its beginnings in Randolph County in 1938/1939, the 50th Anniversary of the Duke Endowment and founding of Duke University in 1974/1975, the 150th Anniversary of its beginnings in Randolph County in 1988/1989, and the 75th Anniversary of the Duke Endowment and founding of Duke University in 1999/2000. The Duke University Anniversaries Collection includes correspondence, clippings, photographs, printed matter, programs, speeches, a sound recording, a diary, acknowledgements from other institutions, a time capsule, and other materials relating to events commemorating the beginnings and founding of Duke University. Major subjects include events planning, fund raising, Duke University, Trinity College (Randolph Co., N.C. and Durham, N.C.), Normal College (Randolph Co., N.C.), Union Institute (Randolph Co., N.C.), and Brown's Schoolhouse (Randolph Co., N.C.). English.
12500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
The collection is open for research, except box 100.19, labeled: "1939-2039. A collection of items presented to the President of Duke University at the Centennial Celebration, April 22, 1939; not to be opened until the occasion of the Two Hundredth Anniversary of the institution."
Provenance
The Duke University Anniversaries Collection was acquired by the University Archives from a variety of sources in 1972-2004, 2008.
Historical Note
Duke University, located in Durham, N.C., was established by James B. Duke in 1924, but it evolved from the following institutions in Randolph County, N.C.: Brown's Schoolhouse, 1838-1839; Union Institute, 1839-1851; Normal College, 1851-1859; and Trinity College, 1859-1892. In 1892, Trinity College relocated from Randolph Co. to the present location of Duke's East Campus in Durham, N.C. Because of this complex history, the University has celebrated anniversaries of two major founding events: the establishment of continuous education at Brown's Schoolhouse in 1838, and the creation of the Duke Endowment, which transformed Trinity College into Duke University in 1924. As a result, the institution commemorated the 100th Anniversary of its beginnings in Randolph County in 1938, the 50th Anniversary of the Duke Endowment and founding of Duke University in 1974, the 150th Anniversary of its beginnings in Randolph County in 1988, and the 75th Anniversary of the Duke Endowment and founding of Duke University in 1999.
In 1838, Methodist and Quaker families in rural Randolph County, N.C. employed Brantley York as a permanent teacher for their subscription school in Brown's Schoolhouse. One hundred years later, Duke University commemorated the 100th Anniversary of its humble beginnings during the 1938/1939 academic year. The Centennial Celebration, a three-day event featuring ceremonies, symposia, lectures, and performances, took place April 21-23, 1939.
During the 1974/1975 academic year, Duke University celebrated the 50th anniversary of its founding. On December 11, 1924, James Buchanan Duke signed an Indenture of Trust creating the Duke Endowment, which established Duke University. The 50th Anniversary Celebration took place the weekend of April 11-13, 1975. Events included a film festival, concerts, convocation, reception, service of worship, and symposia.
Faculty, students, alumni and friends of Duke University travelled to Randolph County, North Carolina, in September 1988, to celebrate the 150th anniversary of Duke's beginnings as a log schoolhouse about 75 miles west of Durham, N.C. Celebration events included a dedication of the Archdale-Trinity Historical Society Museum, birthday parties, tours, lectures, and a symposium.
During the 1999/2000 academic year, Duke University celebrated the 75th anniversary of James B. Duke's creation of the Duke Endowment -- the fund that transformed Trinity College into Duke University. The annual Founder's Day celebration, observed on Sept. 30, 1999, commemorated the Endowment with a series of events focusing on the University's ties to the Duke family.
Collection Overview
The Duke University Anniversaries Collection is divided into four series, arranged by anniversary. 50th Anniversary (1924-1974) of the founding of Duke University series includes correspondence, planning materials, programs, meeting minutes, financial statements, printed matter, and clippings created by the 50th Anniversary Steering and Advisory Committees. Materials range in date from 1973 to 1975. The 75th Anniversary (1924-1999) of the founding of Duke University series includes logos, a commemorative mailing cancellation stamp, a press release, and a sound recording of a speech given by John Koskinen on the Y2K conversion. Materials range in date from 1999 to 2000.
The 100th Anniversary (1838-1938) of the beginnings of Duke University series includes printed materials, correspondence, Centennial Fund records, a diary, publications, invitation lists, congratulations from other institutions, and several complete packets of centennial celebration materials. Also included is a time capsule, labeled: "1939-2039. A collection of items presented to the President of Duke University at the Centennial Celebration, April 22, 1939; not to be opened until the occasion of the Two Hundredth Anniversary of the institution." Materials range in date from 1937 to 1939. Finally, the 150th Anniversary (1838-1988) of the beginnings of Duke University series includes articles, printed matter, correspondence, clippings, subject files, photographs, programs, and financial materials. Major subjects include Sesquicentennial Celebration planning and events, the historical marker for Brown's Schoolhouse, and the plaque and maintenance of the Trinity College Memorial Gazebo in Randolph County. Materials range in date from 1988 to 2000 (bulk 1988-1989). The collection also includes a program from the Centennial Celebration of the relocation of Trinity College to Durham, 1992.
Randolph County (N.C.); Clippings (information artifacts); Sound recordings; Photographs; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.); Duke University. University Archives; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.); Brown's Schoolhouse (Randolph County, N.C.); Duke University -- History; Duke University -- Planning; Duke Endowment
- 50th Anniversary (1924-1974) of the founding of Duke University, 1973-1975
  Biographical/Historical note
  During the 1974/1975 academic year, Duke University celebrated the 50th anniversary of its founding. On December 11, 1924, James Buchanan Duke signed an Indenture of Trust creating the Duke Endowment. This Endowment established Duke University, which was built at Trinity College in Durham, N.C., as a memorial to J. B. Duke's father, Washington Duke, and to the Duke family. The 50th Anniversary Celebration took place the weekend of April 11-13, 1975. Events included a film festival, concerts, convocation, reception, service of worship, and two symposia: The Report of the Carnegie Commission on Higher Education and The Roles of the University in the Post-Colonial World.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series includes correspondence, planning materials, programs, meeting minutes, financial statements, printed matter, and clippings created by the 50th Anniversary Steering and Advisory Committees. Materials range in date from 1973 to 1975. Major subjects include Duke University history and event planning.
  - Programs, April 11-13, 1975 (Box 50.1)
  - Related literature (Box 50.1)
  - Mailing lists (Box 50.1)
  - 50th Anniversary Advisory Committee
    - Program and events (Box 50.1)
    - Correspondence (Box 50.1)
    - Notes and minutes (Box 50.1)
  - 50th Anniversary Steering Committee
    - Correspondence (Box 50.1)
    - Notes and minutes (Box 50.1)
    - Agenda (Box 50.1)
    - Members (Box 50.1)
  - General correspondence (Box 50.1)
  - Reading file (Box 50.1)
  - Clipping, Ruby, April 12, 1975 (Box 50.1)
  - Suggestions (Box 50.2)
  - Advisory Committee (Box 50.2)
  - Minutes and agendas (Box 50.2)
  - Financial materials (Box 50.2)
  - Correspondence with visitors (Box 50.2)
  - Entertainment (Box 50.2)
  - Congratulations from other institutions (Box 50.3)
  - Photographs (contact sheets) (Box 50.3)
  - Steering Committee (Box 50.3)
  - Memoranda and notes (Box 50.3)
  - Guest book (Box 50.3)
  - Calendars of events (Box 50.4)
  - Clippings (Box 50.4)
  - Steering Committee (Box 50.4)
  - 1924-1925 Group (Box 50.4)
  - Convocation (Box 50.4)
- 75th Anniversary (1924-1999) of the founding of Duke University, 1999-2000
  During the 1999/2000 academic year, Duke University celebrated the 75th anniversary of James B. Duke's creation of the Duke Endowment in 1924 -- the fund that transformed Trinity College into Duke University. The annual Founder's Day celebration, observed on Sept. 30, 1999, commemorated the Endowment with a series of events focusing on the University's ties to the Duke family. On Sept. 30, 1999 at the University's Founder's Day convocation in the Chapel, where Dr. James Semans and trustee emeritus Anthony Drexel Duke received honorary degrees from the University. Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans, chair of the Duke Endowment and the granddaughter of Benjamin N. Duke, was the primary speaker at the convocation.
  A bronze statue of Benjamin Duke was unveiled Oct. 2, 1999, in front of Baldwin Auditorium. The son of Washington Duke and the older brother of James B. Duke, Benjamin Duke served on the Board of Trustees longer than any other member of the Duke family.
  Other events included: The Wilson Recreation Center was dedicated Oct. 1, 1999. Television journalist Charlie Rose moderated a panel discussion on economic progress in the Carolinas during the past 75 years. Also, author and anthropologist Mary Catherine Bateson spoke in Baldwin Auditorium Tuesday, Sept. 28, 1999. A special mailing stamp to grace all metered University mail was also created to commemorate the 75th Anniversary.
  Series includes logos, a commemorative mailing cancellation stamp, a press release, and a sound recording of a speech given by John Koskinen on the Y2K conversion, banner, a Durham County Resolution, and framed commemorative telephone directory cover. Additional information on the 75th Anniversary can be found in the Chronicle and the Duke News and Communications website at http://www.duke.edu.
  - Logos (Box 75.1)
  - Envelope with commemorative mail cancellation stamp (Box 75.1)
  - Press release: Duke's 75th Anniversary to be Marked with Commemorative Cancellation Stamp, December 8, 1999 (Box 75.1)
  - Sound recording: Speech by John Koskinen on the federal year 2000 conversion effort, April 14, 2000, [1 cassette tape, approx. 60 minutes; beginning of introduction is missing] (Box 75.1)
    John Koskinen (Class of 1961), Trustee and Chairman of the Board of Trustees, was appointed by President Bill Clinton to lead the President's Council on Year 2000 Conversion. Introduction by David Ferriero, University Librarian.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    A listening copy of the sound recording must be made before use. Please contact University Archives staff.
  - Envelope with commemorative mail cancellation stamp, under the letterhead of the Senior Vice President for Public Affairs and Government Relations (UA2008-0035) (Box 75.2)
  - Durham County Board of County Commissioners Resolution congratulating Duke University on its 75th Anniversary (UA2008-0035) (Box 75.2)
  - 75th Anniversary banner (UA2008-0035) (Box 75.2)
  - Framed Yellow Pages telephone directory cover honoring the 75th Anniversary of Duke University (UA2008-0035) (Box 75.2)
  - Gold cufflinks bearing the 75th Anniversary logo (UA2008-0035) (Box 75.2)
- 100th Anniversary (1838-1938) of the beginnings of Duke University, 1937-1939
  In 1838, Methodist and Quaker families in rural Randolph County, N.C. employed Brantley York as a permanent teacher for their subscription school in Brown's Schoolhouse. One hundred years later, Duke University commemorated the 100th Anniversary of its humble beginnings during the 1938/1939 academic year. The Centennial Celebration, a three-day event featuring ceremonies, symposia, lectures, and performances, took place April 21-23, 1939.
  Series includes printed materials, correspondence, Centennial Fund records, a diary, publications, invitation lists, congratulations from other institutions, and several complete packets of centennial celebration materials. Also included is a time capsule, labeled: "1939-2039. A collection of items presented to the President of Duke University at the Centennial Celebration, April 22, 1939; not to be opened until the occasion of the Two Hundredth Anniversary of the institution."
  - Centennial Fund: Solicitations, contributions, gifts, bequests, fund-raising literature (Box 100.1)
  - Diary, 1938 (Box 100.1)
  - Centennial Fund: Correspondence (Box 100.2)
  - Symposia, 1938-1939 (Box 100.3)
  - Greetings, expenses, delegates, invitation and announcement lists (Box 100.4)
  - Educational Buyers Association, 1939 (Box 100.5)
  - Publications (Box 100.5)
  - Library exhibit, 1939 (Box 100.5)
  - Commencement, 1939 (Box 100.5)
  - Honoring descendants of individuals for whom buildings are named (Box 100.5)
  - Speeches (Box 100.5)
  - Organization: Plan, committees, invitations (Box 100.6)
  - "The Occasion" correspondence and other materials (Box 100.6)
  - Duke University Day, 1937, 1938 (Box 100.6)
  - Odell Day, 1938 (Box 100.6)
  - Trinity College Historical Society Luncheon (Box 100.6)
  - Commencement, 1938 (Box 100.6)
  - Formal opening, 1938 (Box 100.6)
  - Requests for information (Box 100.6)
  - American Math Society, 1939 (Box 100.6)
  - Association of Southeastern Biologists, 1939 (Box 100.6)
  - Addresses (Box 100.7)
  - Complete packets of all printed materials (tickets, programs, etc.) (Box 100.7)
  - Centennial Fund: Correspondence, bulletins, committees, projects (Box 100.8)
  - Programs, symposia, speeches, performances (Box 100.9)
  - Programs, printed material, correspondence (Box 100.1)
  - Songs, stationery, tickets, addresses (Box 100.11)
  - Jerome Dowd letter on "The Formal Ceremonies of the Duke University Centennial" with notes by Mrs. Mary R. Few, wife of President William Preston Few, circa 1939, 1964 (Box 100.11)
  - "...All of the material used in connection with the Duke University Centennial, celebrated during the academic year 1938-39...TO BE KEPT PERMANENTLY IN THE DUKE UNIVERSITY LIBRARY", [2 copies] (Box 100.12)
  - Acknowledgements and congratulations from other institutions (Box 100.13, Oversize-box 100.14-100.15)
  - Plan of organization, packet of materials (Oversize-box 100.16)
  - Packet of materials, Centennial Fund ledger (Oversize-box 100.17)
  - Treasurer's Office packet of centennial materials (Oversize-box 100.18)
  - "1939-2039. A collection of items presented to the President of Duke University at the Centennial Celebration, April 22, 1939; not to be opened until the occasion of the Two Hundredth Anniversary of the institution." (Oversize-box 100.19)
    CLOSED UNTIL 2039.
  - Centennial addresses, December 11, 1937-April 23, 1939 (Oversize-box 100.19)
  - Duke Centennial Celebration scrapbook, 1939 (Box 100.20)
    Scope and Contents
    Assembled by Dorothy Taylor Hayman of Lindenwood College, St. Charles, Mo., as representative of Lindenwood College to the Centennial Celebration.
  - Campus Views Duke University (Centennial Edition), circa 1937-1938 (Box 100.20)
- 150th Anniversary (1838-1988) of the beginnings of Duke University, circa 1988-2000
  Faculty, students, alumni and friends of Duke University travelled to Randolph County, North Carolina, in September 1988, to celebrate the 150th anniversary of Duke's beginnings as a log schoolhouse about 75 miles west of Durham, N.C. The celebration in Trinity -- a rural town that grew up around the college before it moved to Durham and became Duke University -- was among the first of several festivities planned to observe Duke's sesquicentennial. At the celebration, participants walked to the spot where John S. Brown built his one-room subscription schoolhouse and placed a marker commemorating the site where Duke University was born. Although the institution's name has changed in the course of 150 years, university historians have settled on Duke's origins as 1838, when the farming community around Brown's Schoolhouse hired Brantley York to provide continuous education for its children.
  Sesquicentennial events in Trinity, N.C., included a dedication of the Archdale-Trinity Historical Society Museum, a program, a birthday party at the Trinity College Memorial Gazebo, and tours. Other celebration events included a Duke-Durham birthday party, a Blackburn Society meeting, and a seminar, lecture series, and symposium.
  Collection includes articles, printed matter, correspondence, clippings, subject files, photographs, programs, and financial materials. Major subjects include Sesquicentennial Celebration planning and events, the historic marker for Brown's Schoolhouse, and the plaque and maintenance of the Trinity College Memorial Gazebo. Materials range in date from 1988 to 2000 (bulk 1988-1989). The collection also includes a program from the Centennial Celebration of the relocation of Trinity College to Durham, 1992.
  - Articles, printed matter and other material, [3 folders] (Box 150.1)
  - Addition, 2004 [A2004-23]
    - Brown's Schoolhouse marker, 1988 (Box 150.1)
    - Clippings, 1988-1989 and undated (Box 150.1)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1989, 1996 (Box 150.1)
    - Photographs (Box 150.1)
    - Trinity Gazebo maintenance and plaques, 1982-2000, [2 folders] (Box 150.1)
    - Centennial Celebration of the Relocation of Trinity College to Durham, 1992 (Box 150.1)